A Guide to the Lawrence B. Dunham Papers FA041
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lawrence B. Dunham papers
1887-1971, bulk 1914-1959
Rockefeller Archive Center
Dunham, Lawrence Boardman
FA041
2.61 Cubic Feet 4 document cases
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Lawrence B. Dunham papers were donated to the Rockefeller Foundation Archives in May 1971 and June 1977 by Mrs. Lawrence B. Dunham.
Arrangement
The Lawrence B. Dunham Papers are arranged alphabetically by topic (e.g., Bureau of Social Hygiene, Domestic Relations Court, Military Service) or document type (e.g., Articles and Addresses, Correspondence, Scrapbook).
Scope and Contents
The Lawrence B. Dunham Papers document the wide range of activities in which Dunham engaged during his lifetime. The papers include correspondence, memoranda, reports, drafts of speeches, clippings, pamphlets, and a scrapbook. Most of this material postdates 1934. Approximately one-quarter of this collection consists of private correspondence; another quarter of it covers Dunham's tenure on the Domestic Relations Court of New York City. There are no separate items regarding Dunham's association with the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, and his work as Director of the Bureau of Social Hygiene is not amply documented here. Users of this collection are advised to supplement their research on any of Dunham's activities for which separate folders exist by examining the correspondence folders covering the same period.
Biographical / Historical
Lawrence Boardman Dunham was born in Newton, Massachusetts, on July 18, 1882, and received the Ph.B degree from Yale University in 1904. He graduated from the New York Law School in 1907 and entered into practice in New York City until 1913, when he was appointed Deputy Commissioner of Bridges for New York City. The following year, he was named Deputy Commissioner of the Police, a post he retained until 1922. On June 10, 1915, he married (Margaret) Vrayling Putnam; their family included three children.
Dunham's tenure with the Police Department was interrupted by his service in the U.S. Army during World War I. In 1918 he served with the rank of Major in the intelligence division and was stationed primarily at Hoboken, New Jersey. Upon his resignation from the Police Department in 1922, he joined the G.M.P. Murphy Company, and until 1925 was president of the Caddo Central (later Clayton) Oil and Refining Company.
From 1925 until 1928 Dunham was associated with the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, directing studies of crime and juvenile delinquency. For the next six years (1928-1934), he was Director of the Bureau of Social Hygiene, where he developed programs reflecting his interests while involved with the LSRM. During 1931-1932 he also served as a technical advisor to the U.S. delegation to the League of Nations Opium Convention in Geneva, Switzerland.
Dunham acted as campaign manager in the Bronx for Fiorello H. LaGuardia's first mayoral contest in 1933. During the first 16 months of LaGuardia's term, he served as Executive Secretary to the Mayor. On April 16, 1935, he was appointed City Magistrate, and on September 23 of the same year was named to the Domestic Relations Court of New York City.
In 1942, Judge Dunham reentered active service with the U.S. Army and was engaged in intelligence work with the General Staff Corps, serving with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. He directed counterespionage and anti-sabotage operations on both the east and west coast of the United States. In 1945 he was awarded the U.S. Legion of Merit. After the war, he retired from the bench, and died on August 8, 1959, at Plattsburgh, New York.
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 2A 18
New York (N.Y.); World War I; Yale University; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Domestic Relations Court of New York City
- Articles and Addresses, approximately 1927-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bureau of Social Hygiene, 1916, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bureau of Social Hygiene, 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Claddo Central/Clayton Oil and Refining Company, 1919-1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clippings, 1915-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1914-1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1934-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
- Domestic Relations Court, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
- Domestic Relations Court, 1939-1944 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Family History, 1887-1959 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Golf, 1946-1959 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Law Practice, 1907-1908 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Military Service - World War I, 1917-1919, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Military Service - World War II - Formerly Classified, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
- Military Service - World War II - Formerly Classified, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 20a)
- Military Service - World War II, 1943-1945, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Miscellany, 1912-1956 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Narcotics, 1931-1932, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- New York Police Department, 1913-1917, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Real Estate and Financial Material, 1925-1953 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Scrapbook, 1933-1937 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Scrapbook, 1933-1937 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Scope and Contents
  Photocopies of clippings.
- Secretary to the Mayor, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Testimonials, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Unitarian Church, 1945-1971 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Yale University, 1904-1959 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Yawl Blueprints and Agreement, 1936-1939 (Box 5)
- Certificate of Membership in Delta Phi Fraternity, 1901 (Box 5)
- Family Tree (Box 5)
- Yale Diploma, 1904 (Box 5)
- Certificate of Admission to the New York Bar Association, 1913 (Box 5)
- Certificate of Appointment to Narcotics Conference, 1931 (Box 5)
- Certificates of Appointment to New York City positions, 1934-1935 (Box 5)
- Lawrence B. Dunham photographs, ca. 1885-1957; 1011; Dunham, Lawrence Boardman; 1 folder
  Law enforcement, groups, recreation, boats, awards, ceremonies.
  Scope and Contents note
  57 photographs, consisting of portraits, portrayals of ceremonial occasions, yachting events, and Yale University class reunions.
  Biographical / Historical
  Lawrence Boardman Dunham was born in Newton, Massachusetts, on July 18, 1882, and received the Ph.B degree from Yale University in 1904. He graduated from the New York Law School in 1907 and entered into practice in New York City until 1913, when he was appointed Deputy Commissioner of Bridges for New York City. The following year, he was named Deputy Commissioner of the Police, a post he retained until 1922. On June 10, 1915, he married (Margaret) Vrayling Putnam; their family included three children.
  Dunham's tenure with the Police Department was interrupted by his service in the U.S. Army during World War I. In 1918 he served with the rank of Major in the intelligence division and was stationed primarily at Hoboken, New Jersey. Upon his resignation from the Police Department in 1922, he joined the G.M.P. Murphy Company, and until 1925 was president of the Caddo Central (later Clayton) Oil and Refining Company.
  From 1925 until 1928 Dunham was associated with the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, directing studies of crime and juvenile delinquency. For the next six years (1928-1934), he was Director of the Bureau of Social Hygiene, where he developed programs reflecting his interests while involved with the LSRM. During 1931-1932 he also served as a technical advisor to the U.S. delegation to the League of Nations Opium Convention in Geneva, Switzerland.
  Dunham acted as campaign manager in the Bronx for Fiorello H. LaGuardia's first mayoral contest in 1933. During the first 16 months of LaGuardia's term, he served as Executive Secretary to the Mayor. On April 16, 1935, he was appointed City Magistrate, and on September 23 of the same year was named to the Domestic Relations Court of New York City.
  In 1942, Judge Dunham reentered active service with the U.S. Army and was engaged in intelligence work with the General Staff Corps, serving with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. He directed counterespionage and anti-sabotage operations on both the east and west coast of the United States. In 1945 he was awarded the U.S. Legion of Merit. After the war, he retired from the bench, and died on August 8, 1959, at Plattsburgh, New York.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research.
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  Collection is open for scholarly research. Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
  Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
  - Lawrence B. Dunham, c. 1885-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)